(410) 531-1475 <u>king_jm@msn.com</u>

Public & Private Sectors · Public Health Research · Project Management

Comprehensive academic background combined with several years of experience and accomplishment in supporting and leading public health research initiatives, utilizing data from sources such as national health/healthcare surveys and surveillance systems. Highly organized with the ability to manage multiple research and data analysis projects effectively and in a timely manner. Effective communicator, with active clearance and certification in human subjects research, HIPAA, and the Privacy Act for security assurance that readily distills complex material into clear and concise reports, briefings, and presentations for various audiences. Core competencies include:

- Secret/SSBI Clearance
- Quantitative Analysis
- Qualitative Analysis
- Team Building/Leadership
- Data Collection Design
- Collaborative Problem Solver
- Health Surveillance & Studies
- Outcome & Process Program Evaluation
- Excellent People Skills

EDUCATION

TULANE UNIVERSITY, New Orleans, Louisiana

Master of Public Health, Epidemiology (summa cum laude)

~ with a subspecialty in Clinical Epidemiology

SPELMAN COLLEGE, Atlanta, Georgia

**Bachelor of Science, Biology*

**minor in Biochemistry*

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

HEALTH RESEARCHER III

MAY 2022 - APRIL 2024

RELI Group, Inc., 5520 Research Park Drive, Suite 105, Catonsville, Maryland 21228. (40 hours/week)

Providing technical support and assistance to the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) 2022 Qualified Health Plan (QHP) Enrollee Experience Survey and the Division of Health Care Statistics at the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) regarding the planning, development, implementation, and conduct of National Health Care Surveys that duties encompass, but not limited to, the following:

- Assisting in identifying data priorities in the areas of healthcare medical conditions/utilization and conducting
 health services research/surveillance using data from the National Health Care Surveys [e.g., National Hospital
 Ambulatory Medical Care Survey (NHAMCS) and National Ambulatory Medical Care Survey (NAMCS)].
- Performing SAS/SUDAAN descriptive statistics data analyses/data validation and special tabulations on issues of
 concern (e.g., infectious and/or chronic disease estimation, provider and emergency department visits), including
 quality control and assurance procedures, and SQL data linkage matters such as the restricted-use linked National
 Hospital Care Survey (NHCS) with CMS Medicare administrative data and National Death Index (NDI) data.
- Contributing to intra-agency requests, AHRQ's annual *National Healthcare Quality and Disparities Report* (*NHQDR*) updated trending data/tables; manuscript/report development for publication by NCHS and/or professional journals (e.g., NCHS Data Brief titled, *Emergency Department Visit Rates by Selected Characteristics: United States*, 2021); and NAMCS—Health Center Component dashboard project with maternal and child health content and measures.
- Responding to incoming internal and/or external data requests/inquiries concerning National Health Care Surveys.
- Preparing/validating public use products (e.g., FastStats/web tables, NCHS Stats of the Month, 2023 NAMCS) with associated technical documentation and utilizing restricted-use files from the NCHS Research Data Center (RDC).

PUBLIC HEALTH EPIDEMIOLOGIST

NOVEMBER 2015 – SEPTEMBER 2021

Cherokee Nation Businesses, Cherokee Nation Strategic Programs, 2511 Jefferson Davis Highway, Suite 540, Arlington, VA 22202. (40 hours/week)

Note: Gap Period – Due to Company's Contract Expiration on September 30, 2021

Assisting on-site, exclusively, as an Epidemiologist within the Data Analysis Unit (DOED) of the Drug and Chemical Evaluation Section (DOE) providing public health and scientific technical support and assistance to the entire programmatic senior leadership and staff (i.e., chemists and pharmacologists) and task priorities such as drug scheduling actions/documents, domestic and international presentations, talking points, and content for events such as U.S. Congressional/federal expert testimonials) in response to the Drug Enforcement Administration, Diversion Control Division mission.

- Aiding as DOE's public health point-of-contact and/or technical expert with respect to the *International Classification of Diseases, Clinical Modification (ICD-10-CM)* and query systems/reporting tools such as *CDC WONDER (Wide-ranging Online Data for Epidemiologic Research)* for National Vital Statistics System (NVSS) data; non-fatal/fatal drug overdose trending/rates; national surveys/studies [e.g., National Survey on Drug Use and Health (NSDUH) and Monitoring the Future (MTF)]; poison control center, IQVIA prescriptions dispensed, medical claims, and emergency visit data; conducting data collection, analysis, and statistical testing techniques (e.g., tests of significant, correlations); literature reviews/Internet research, policy analysis and/or recommendations; and update status briefings and/or presentations with various DEA staff personnel/audiences.
- Ongoing monitoring and surveillance and routinely performing drug seizure reporting search queries/data requests (e.g., frequencies/counts) within the *National Forensic Laboratory Information System (NFLIS)* and the *System to Retrieve Information from Drug Evidence (STRIDE)/STARLiMS* surveillance databases for tasks such as generating restricted-use or public access data files and developing and designing tracking and trending surveillance graphs/maps for drug scheduling document development, review, and quality control/assurance procedures.
- Updating the 41st 43rd World Health Organization (WHO) Expert Committee on Drug Dependence (ECDD) Surveillance Listing of Substances, 2013–2020 for proposed Treaty Convention decisions (e.g., 1961 and 1971 Conventions) and regularly tracking newly emerging novel psychoactive substances (NPS) for the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime Early Warning Advisory (UNODC EWA) initiative by utilizing drug seizure reporting outcomes in law enforcement surveillance databases.
- Serving-on/attending Interagency Committee on Drug Control (ICDC) quarterly meetings along with regularly scheduled DOE Section meetings, DOED Unit meetings, and as a member of the DOE Emerging Drugs Working Group that included designing and developing the working group's Microsoft (MS) Access database for drug and chemical substances, and the redesign of NFLIS and its Oracle database.

SENIOR ASSOCIATE

JUNE 2013 – NOVEMBER 2015

King Family Business, Silver Spring, Maryland, 20903. (40 hours/week; Currently Intermittent)

- Established terms/conditions, mission, and strategic roadmap for charitable funding.
- Oversaw and monitored expense budget/investment plan.
- Participated/coordinated events/activities for community and public health outreach, awareness, and social change.
- Supplying resources to outreach organizations and/or foundations for their mission and objectives.

SENIOR CONSULTANT AUGUST 2010 – MAY 2013

Booz Allen Hamilton, One Preserve Parkway, Suite 200, Rockville, Maryland, 20852. (40 hours/week)

- Served as a Lead Epidemiologist within the Department of Defense (DoD), Armed Forces Health Surveillance Center (AFHSC), Epidemiology and Analysis Division and proactively supported the TRICARE Management Activity (TMA)/Force Health Protection and Readiness (FHP & R), Global Health Surveillance Unit Initiative.
- Conducted SAS/SQL programming of source files utilizing the Defense Medical Surveillance System (DMSS), analyzed and de-identified data for Services' ad hoc data dissemination requests and aggregate reports (e.g., descriptive statistics), performed QC/QA reviews, and drafted AFHSC progress reports.
- For the Defense Centers of Excellence for Psychological Health and Traumatic Brain Injury (DCoE), delivered program strategic development and outcome evaluations for service members' suicide prevention/resilience programs (i.e., ACE, Never Leave A Marine Behind, and Soldier 360).
- Developed evidence-based outcome and process performance capability measures and conducted environmental scan research/literature reviews for the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), Division of State and Local Readiness, Public Health Emergency Preparedness (PHEP) cooperative agreement initiative and the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response (ASPR) Hospital Preparedness Program (HPP) grant alignment strategic initiative to institute and enhance national preparedness and emergency response procedures and policies.
- Performed gap analysis on all 15 PHEP capability performance measures, contributed to the development of an online questionnaire for PHEP awardee/workgroup feedback, and served as contributing researcher/writer for the PHEP Budget Year One Performance Measure guidance document.
- Executed policy analysis of the *Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act* (PPACA) provisions and fiscal funding with respect to health disparities.

SENIOR EVALUATOR JULY 2007 – MARCH 2010

AFYA, Inc., 8101 Sandy Springs Road, Suite 301, Laurel, Maryland, 20707. (40 hours/week) Note: Gap Period – Due to U.S. Economic Recession Period

- Provided research/epidemiologic research, program evaluation, comparative effectiveness research, and project
 management support along with technical briefings/presentations to government officials and/or healthcare
 organizations, as noted below; developing strategic evaluation plans and logic models for outcome and process
 evaluations, designing survey instruments including online questionnaires and relational databases, preparing
 focus groups discussions questions/needs assessments, and conducting qualitative and quantitative analysis
 primarily in SPSS for projects.
- Served as a standing member of AFYA's Marketing and New Business Development Committee.
- Provided evaluation research support to the American Lung Association's District of Columbia Tobacco Free Families Campaign, a partnership with the American Cancer Society (ACS) and D.C. Department of Health, including designing/developing supplemental survey questions for the D.C. survey administration of the Youth Risk Behavior Surveillance System (YRBSS); the Public Health Service (PHS) Office of Women's Health Girl-Adolescent Health and Wellness Initiative; the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) Portfolio Analysis and National Guideline Clearinghouse Evaluation Projects; Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA) Recovery initiative; and the CDC National Center for Injury Prevention and Control Partnership Training Evaluation Project for policy and procedural improvements.

PROGRAM ANALYST MAY 2006 – FEBRUARY 2007

National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, Rheumatic Diseases Branch, 6701 Democracy Boulevard, Suite 800, Bethesda, Maryland 20892. (40 hours/week)

Note: Gap Period – Temporary/Conditional position due to expansion of Program that lacked an epidemiology focus & Health Condition Treatment

- Although brief due to the piloting of its extramural program expansion and lack of epidemiologic work/initiatives, provided scientific and analytical support concerning arthritis, musculoskeletal and skin diseases for the NIAMS extramural program portfolio.
- Coordinated, reviewed, and assessed status of progress reports for extramural program administration of grants, training grant awards, and other funding sources.
- Utilized the NIH clinicaltrials.gov web site to provide technical assistance to the public and coordinated meetings and supplied technical support to workgroups.
- Represented NIAMS on the Lupus Federal Working Group, National Arthritis Data Workgroup, the Trans-NIH National Health Interview Survey (NHIS) Interest Group, the Healthy People 2010 Focus Area 2 Workgroup, and the NIH Minority Health & Health Disparities Research Forum Planning Committee.

RESEARCH ANALYST/PATIENT NAVIGATOR PROGRAM COORDINATOR

AUGUST 2004 – MAY 2006

NOVA Research Company, 4600 East-West Highway, Suite 700, Bethesda, Maryland, 20814. (40 hours/week)

Provided technical support and assistance to the National Cancer Institute (NCI), Center to Reduce Cancer Health Disparities (CRCHD) under contract and coordinated daily program activities for the Patient Navigator Research Program (PNRP), particularly with federal officials (e.g., program directors) within the Disparities Research Branch at CRCHD.

- Served as Coordinator of the PNRP, a cooperative agreement, studying the time to reduce patient's cancer screening to cancer diagnosis to cancer treatment for four cancer types (i.e., breast, cervical, colorectal, and prostate) with a patient navigator intervention model to reduce/mitigate barriers (e.g., financial, transportation, healthcare bias) that contributed to the Patient Navigator Outreach and Chronic Disease Prevention Act of 2005.
- Analyzed grant applications and proposed budgets in preparation for scientific peer review process.
- Collaborated with the NIH Scientific Review Administrator (SRA) and Grants Management Specialist along with ongoing communication with grantees/Principal Investigators.
- Wrote and/or contributed to newsletter articles for the *NCI Cancer Bulletin* and the *NIH Record*, announcing the Patient Navigator Program and/or grant awarded institutions.
- Researched and analyzed Surveillance Epidemiology & End Results (SEER) cancer/health disparities data including PNRP study subjects' outcome data.
- Researched status of IRB assurances and acted as liaison when IRB assurances were inactive or expired within the Office for Human Research Protections (OHRP) database.

EPIDEMIOLOGIST II MAY 2004 – AUGUST 2004

Maryland Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, Community Health Administration, Epidemiology Disease Control Programs, Division of Outbreak Investigation, 201 West Preston Street, Baltimore, Maryland, 21201. (40 hours/week)

- Conducted site visits to local county health departments to audit and evaluate the quality of outbreak investigations and recordkeeping for state compliance.
- Supplied state-level technical assistance and support to local county health departments and conducted epidemiologic investigations of communicable infectious disease and foodborne outbreaks.
- Provided Maryland State support to the CDC Office of Infectious Diseases for a national foodborne salmonella outbreak and served as Lead Epidemiologist on a norovirus outbreak initiated at a food establishment.
- Utilized federal initiatives such as the Hazard Analysis and Critical Control Point (HACCP) and the Electronic Foodborne Outbreak Reporting System (eFORS).
- Wrote and disseminated official State health alert correspondence to local/county health departments based on recall/health alert facsimile transmissions from the FDA, Division of Federal-State Relations (DFSR).
- Served on Epidemiology Disease Control Programs on-call staff rotation and officially trained Syndromic Surveillance Team for Homeland Security and Bioterrorism Preparedness activities.

HEALTH RESEARCH ANALYST II/ ACTING DEPUTY DIRECTOR DECEMBER 1998 – May 2004

Northrop Grumman Information Technology (formerly known as Logicon/R.O.W. Sciences, Inc.), 1700 Research Boulevard, Suite 400, Rockville, Maryland, 20850. (40 hours/week)

Responsible for carrying out the technical research and evaluation mission/aims, managing daily operations and overseeing staff support activities along with technical presentations/briefings within the Health Research & Analysis Division, Epidemiology Unit as Acting Deputy Director and within the Tobacco Control Program Services Division as a Health Research Analyst II.

- Served as Lead Epidemiologist/Deputy Director of the *Study of Possible Long-Term Effects Associated with Administration of Multiple Vaccines in the Special Immunizations Program (SIP)* for the U.S. Army Medical Research Institute of Infectious Diseases (USAMRIID).
- Assisted as Task Manager of the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Center for Devices and Radiological Health (CDRH) Access to Mammography Services Survey to assess the impact of the Mammography Quality Standards Act (MOSA).
- Developed and designed survey instruments for Office of Management and Budget (OMB) clearance along with data analysis plans (e.g., descriptive statistics, multivariate analysis), coding guides/data dictionaries, and training/operating procedural manuals, in addition to, providing sampling, data collection, coding, data entry and analysis, and final report writing for assigned surveys/studies.
- Performed as Task Manager/researcher and relational database designer/collaborator on an epidemiologic
 research project for the National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR) and the National Center
 for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Division of Oral Health and as contributing writer for *Oral Health U.S.*, 2003 annual report, featuring statistics (e.g., frequencies, rates, proportions) and trends for a
 selection of dental and craniofacial healthcare and oral health status indicators and by select demographic
 characteristics.
- Analyzed national data in SAS from the *National Health Interview Survey* (NHIS), the *Medical Expenditure Panel Survey* (MEPS), the *National Hospital Ambulatory Medical Care Survey* (NHAMCS), the *Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System* (BRFSS), and the *National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey* (NHANES) for the abovementioned oral health annual report.
- As Data Analyst/Interviewer, for the Social Security Administration's pilot of psychological assessments for the *Mental Health Treatment Study* as well as for several research projects for the CDC Office on Smoking and Health, conducted tasks such as preparing data files for survey data collection and/or sampling, determining sample size, and designing relational databases while maintaining data quality control and assurance procedures.
- Aided as a peer review workgroup coordinator for the 2002 National Conference on Tobacco or Health.

OTHER INFORMATION

<u>Security Clearance Information</u>: Secret Clearance (Active), OPM/DOJ, November 2015 (initial), September 2020 (updated); DISCO, Booz Allen Hamilton, June 2011; Single Scope Background Investigation (SSBI), OPM, National Institutes of Health, 2006; Background Investigation Check, OPM, Northrop Grumman Information Technology, 2000

<u>Technical Training Coursework:</u> Lean Six Sigma; DoD Privacy Act and HIPAA Operations Training and Recertification; NIH Protecting Human Research Participants Certification; Microsoft Office Project Training; HHS Basic Project Officer's Training; NCI Grant Budget and Policy Issues Training; NCI Extramural Staff Orientation

<u>Computer Skills/Training</u>: BMDP, Epi Info, GIS, Internet, Medline, Microsoft Office Professional (Access, Excel, Outlook, PowerPoint, Project, SharePoint, Word), Minitab, NVivo, Power BI, PubMed, QSR NUD*IST, R, SAS, SPSS, SUDAAN, Tableau

Key Presentations/Briefings:

- Qualitative Methods and Strategies in Research, Health Research & Analysis Division, Northrop Grumman Information Technology, 2000.
- *Clinical Dental Procedures and Indices in NHANES*, Epidemiology Unit, Health Research & Analysis Division, Northrop Grumman Information Technology, 2002.
- District of Columbia Tobacco Free Families Campaign Preliminary Findings, American Lung Association, 2008.
- Epidemiologic Surveillance in Public Safety and Public Health, Diversion Control Division, Drug Enforcement Administration, 2019.
- 2019 Update and Trend on Drug Overdose Deaths, Drug and Chemical Evaluation Section, Diversion Control Division, Drug Enforcement Administration, 2021.